<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The ministers portion· By William Sclater. Batchelar of Diuinity and minister of the word of God at Pitmister in Somerset</title>
            <author>Sclater, William, 1575-1626.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1612</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 100 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11600</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21841</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116822</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852038</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852038</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17338</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11600)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17338)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1187:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The ministers portion· By William Sclater. Batchelar of Diuinity and minister of the word of God at Pitmister in Somerset</title>
                  <author>Sclater, William, 1575-1626.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 49, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Ioseph Barnes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1612.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tithes --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17338:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17338:1"/>
            <p>THE MINISTERS PORTION.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY</hi> WILLIAM SCLATER. BATCHELAR OF DIVINITY <hi>and Miniſter of the word of God at</hi> PIT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MISTER <hi>in Somerſet.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of University of Oxford</figDesc>
               <p>AC: OX</p>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>AT OXFORD,</hi> Printed by Ioſeph Barnes. 1612:</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17338:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17338:2"/>
            <head>TO THE WORSHIPFVLL M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>THOMAS SOVTHCOT</hi> ESQVIRE, at MOONES-OTERY in <hi>Devon,</hi> grace and peace.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, when I firſt meditated what at your inſtance I reviſed, and now al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt enforced, publiſh: I expected co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions from Mammoniſtes, and ſcarſe hoped to perſwade men ſavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of better things. Such a holdfaſt is covetouſnes; ſo incredulous is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice. Farther oppoſition from bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and Iudicious men, was as farre from my thought, as I am in this point from their opinion. But <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith wel;<note place="margin">Aug. cont Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſ. leg &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet. li. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Deus donat prodeſſe nobis non ſolûm quod docet ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas, verùm etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quod obſtrepit vanitas.</hi> And ſuch oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings againſt truth are thus farre for it, that they occaſion more intentiue ſearch, and clearer diſcovery of the truth. My purpoſe is not to preſcribe to any mans faith. <hi>Nam quis ego ſum?</hi> Even the leaſt of Gods little ones. Yet as one that hath obtained mercy of God to be faithfull, let me en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat this favour from men, to be heard on even termes, with me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I freely confeſſe, of far greater gifts, yet, as I thinke, having no ſuch evidence in this point, to carry away ſo ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmooth
<pb facs="tcp:17338:3"/> a concluſion of ſuch dependance. This, I hope, will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to any impartiall reader, that the reaſons here brought for tythes, are much nearer to demo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtratiue, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe againſt them are to probable arguments. My poore paines I haue inſcribed to your worſhip, as for many your well deſervings of me, and the Church of God; ſo for that you firſt vrged a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view of the firſt rude draught, and haue given me ſo manie occaſions to thinke you will not be the laſt in practiſing this vnprofitable profitable concluſion, when once your Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhalbee convinced. And though I loue not to bee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emptory, (for I know mine owne blindnes) yet this I thinke I may ſay; the reaſons on both ſides being peized in even bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, there will ſcarce be left place for an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or ſuſpenſe of Iudgment, except men be reſolute to hold their concluſion in deſpight of all contrary premiſes. Now the God of all truth direct our hearts to the knowledge and loue, and obedience of the truth. And the ſame God that begun his good worke in you, confirme, and perfect it to the day of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your worſhips in the trueſt loue, <hi>WILLIAM SCLATER.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:17338:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1. Cor. 9.13, 14.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> Do yee not know that they which miniſter about the holy things, liue of the things of the Temple? and they which wait at the Altar, are partakers with the Altar?</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> Eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo hath the Lord ordained, that they which preach the Goſpell ſhould liue of the Goſpell.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His whole period of Scripture, from ver. 5. to 15. conſiſts of one diſcrete axiome, in ſumme this: Though I <hi>Paule</hi> haue power and right to liue at the charge of the Church, ver. 5. yet I haue not vſed that power, ver. 12. the reaſon whereof he giues; <hi>Leaſt hee ſhould hinder the Goſpell of Chriſt,</hi> through ſuſpicion of mercenary. Affection in preaching. Now for that it might be queſtioned whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he had any ſuch right or no, hee avowes the truth of his title; by arguments <hi>à genere,</hi> he was an Apoſtle &amp; preacher of the Goſpell, ver. 1. <hi>Ergo</hi> had right. 2. preve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly, <hi>à pari,</hi> in the practiſe of others; ver. 5.6. <hi>as well as Peter &amp;c.</hi> And for that the claime might not ſeeme e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall betwixt <hi>Paule</hi> and <hi>Cephas</hi> and the Lords brethren, he ſheweth that to every miniſter of the Goſpell, main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance is due for their worke ſake. By reaſons, 1. From voice of nature and conſent of nations in other ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blant imployments<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>as who goes to war, &amp;c.</hi> ver. 7. 2. From mandate of the law of God. <hi>Saith not the law of God the ſame, &amp;c.</hi> ver. 8.9.10. 3. From excellency of bleſſings conferred by Miniſters, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared with qualitie of things exacted for recompence; <hi>If we ſowe ſpirituall things &amp;c.</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:17338:4"/> ver. 11. 4. From allowed practiſe of Leviticall miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, ver. 13. Laſtly, from expreſſe ordinance of Chriſt, <hi>the Lord hath ordained, &amp;c.</hi> ver. 14. this the frame of the text.</p>
            <p>Out of all which amounts this plaine Apoſtolicall concluſion; That <hi>maintenance is due from people to Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters for their worke ſake.</hi> Other proofes then are here ſet downe, it is needleſſe to vſe. Wee haue here more then two or three witneſſes, fiue ſound reaſons inforcing it. The bare word of an Apoſtle is enough to carry a point more doubtfull. How much more ſhould it ſway with vs, when Gods ſpirit that ſpake in them, is pleaſed by ſo many reaſons to avouch it? Is it not then a ſound tene<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t (trow we) of ſome, that Miniſters maintenance is meer almes? and that in iuſtice, and as due, they can challenge nothing for their labour in the word and doctrine?</p>
            <p n="1">1 Where then is <hi>Paules</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, his right, lawful power and authoritie, to receaue maintenance from the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, v. 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>2? How ſaith our Saviour, they are <hi>worthie of their hire,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Luk 9 7.</note> 
               <hi>Paule worthy of double honour</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">1. Tim 5.17.</note>? 3 What great thing was this that <hi>Paule</hi> did in taking no maintenance, ver. 12.15? By theſe mens divinitie he had right to none.</p>
            <p n="2">2 And what ods is there betwixt this beggerly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of thoſe old beggers, and that of late ſeparats, that make it Chriſts ordinance for Miniſters to liue of their peoples voluntary contribution; and hold it as Chriſts owne Canon, that no ſet maintenance ſhoulde be allotted vs, no not by humane ordinance, but the people left at liberty to giue or not to giue, to giue much or little, otherwiſe then ſelfe devotion ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline them? May I not ſay of this and the former as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> of <hi>Pharaos</hi> dreames,<note n="c" place="margin">Gen 41.25.</note> 
               <hi>the dreames are one?</hi> Words
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:17338:4"/> onely haue made a variation. Miniſters muſt liue of the peoples voluntary contribution: me thinkes I heare <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Pauls</hi> tenour for almes,<note n="d" place="margin">2. Cor. 9.7.</note> 
               <hi>As every man wiſheth in his heart ſo let him giue.</hi> Their reaſons had need be pregna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: let vs view them. 1. Forſooth the Apoſtles thus lived. <hi>Reſp.</hi> J yeeld it of ſome of them: yea ſometimes made their own hands miniſter to their neceſſities: why force they vs not to mechanicall trades? For ſo lived ſome A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles. But 1 they had power to exact maintenance, ſith they had right<note n="e" place="margin">1. Cor. 9.4, 5</note> to haue it. 2, Occaſionall practiſe binds not to imitation, but in occurrence of like occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons When ſcandall inforceth to forbeare exaction, we will herein follow their holy example, leaſt by any meanes we hinder the Goſpell; ver. 12. and farther then this, their example vrgeth not.</p>
            <p>Their ſecond reaſon is this: becauſe it muſt be ſeene that what the people giue this way, they giue of loue, not for feare of the law. <hi>Reſp.</hi> and it muſt bee ſeene that the <hi>people</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Pſ. 110.3.</note> 
               <hi>come willingly at the daies of aſſembling.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Magiſtrats may not compell by autoritie to ſerue the Lord as<note n="g" place="margin">2. Chr. 34.31 32.33.</note> good <hi>Ioſiah</hi> did, for <hi>now they beare the ſword in vaine.</hi> But thus J reaſon and ſo leaue them.</p>
            <p>To every duty Magiſtrats may bind by lawe, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel by puniſhment. Yeelding maintenance to Miniſters is a dutie. Therefore thereto may Magiſtrates binde by lawes. <hi>Miſerum eſt</hi> (ſaith the Poet) <hi>alienâ vivere quadrâ:</hi> if for any, miſerable; ſure moſt for a miniſter. This if any thing, breeds right trencher Chaplens, &amp; would ſoon fill the Church with ſweet tongued &amp; mealemouthed preachers.</p>
            <p n="3">3 I may not leaue vtterly vntouched our peoples,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17338:5"/> whether ignorant or affectionate errour: that thinke of their payments to Miniſters, as of almes to their beadſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; forſooth we liue by them. I ſay no more but this, 1, If<note n="h" place="margin">1. Cor. 9.11.</note> we by them in carnall things, they by vs in ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al. Is the barter ſo hard as ſhould occaſion exprobratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? <hi>2. Not by you but by the Lords ordinance</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">1. Cor. 9.14.</note> ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle.</p>
            <p>And that Lord that hath given to the people the nines; hath allotted to vs <hi>(audacter dicam)</hi> the tenthes as ours.</p>
            <p n="4">4 J would faine leaue this reproofe, but that J ſee the errour hath wound it ſelfe into the minds of many of holy profeſſion and practiſe, who yet delight to haue Miniſters acknowledge a debt, even for receit of dues; and deſire to haue conſcience free from all bonds more then of humane lawes, in this matter of recompencing our labours. Jf ought come elſe more then law or cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, if but a cup of cold water; they ſupererogate ſure<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly in reſpect of the Miniſter. They much forget who ſaid,<note n="k" place="margin">Philemo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 19</note> 
               <hi>thou oweſt vnto me even thy owne ſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And of the generall thus farre. Now the inquiry J take it, is not impertinent here; ſith maintenance is due to Miniſters for their worke ſake, what portion or qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie that is, that by Gods ordinance belongs to them. And me thinkes in a dutie ſo generally, though plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taught, the conſcience of the hearers ſhould deſire a more particular direction. Yee will therefore (I hope) giue leaue ſomething more particularly to examin the matter. And herein J hold it not amiſſe, firſt to propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d what is yeelded on all ſides, where is any ſoundneſſe of iudgement. 2. Then to adde ſome other principles, as
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17338:5"/> plainely taught in the Scriptures of the new Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Laſtly to enquire and reſolue of the particular.</p>
            <p>The grants on all ſides are theſe. 1. That there is a maintenance<note n="h" place="margin">1. Cor. 9.4, 5 ad 15.</note> in iuſtice due to Miniſters and their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies for their worke ſake.</p>
            <p n="2">2 It is yeelded that it muſt be competent; not only for ſupply of naturall neceſſities, but for their furniture to every good work of their calling.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That it muſt be<note n="m" place="margin">1. Tim. 5.17 18.</note> liberall; not ſuch as every nig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardly minde will iudge convenient and competent.</p>
            <p>To which grants, let me adde theſe poſtulata, as plainely determined in the Scriptures.</p>
            <p n="1">1 That to the Miniſters of the Goſpell belongs a maintenance as large, as to the Leviticall Prieſthood; this me thinkes, excellencie of miniſtery,<note n="n" place="margin">2. Cor. 3. 1. Cor. 9.</note> and bleſſings conferred thereby, enforceth.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That this maintenance muſt riſe out of<note n="n" place="margin">Gal. 6.6.</note> all and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very the goods of al and every of the people inſtructed.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Shall I adde another to me ſeeming more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable? that is, that the Lord hath as certainely provided for our maintenance vnder the Goſpel, as for theirs vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the law. For had the Lord leſſe care of vs? was there leſſe need in reſpect of the peoples backwardneſſe? no. But he entruſted magiſtrats with that care. <hi>Reſp.</hi> And were there not Magiſtrats among the Iewes?</p>
            <p n="4">4 That the Lord in the Leviticall law made proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for vs that were to miniſter in the Goſpell. Its cleere by the Apoſtles twiſe alleaging that ordinance of<note n="o" place="margin">1. Cor. 9.9. 1. Tim. 5.18.</note> 
               <hi>not muzling the mouth of the oxe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus farre I thinke we walke ſafely, ſith in the very ſteps of the holy Ghoſt leading vs in the newe Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17338:6"/> Let vs now deſcend toward the particular.</p>
            <p>Some tumbling downe headlong rather then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending, reſolue of a competency indeterminate; ſo the allowance be competent, all is well. <hi>Reſp.</hi> Then in caſe of this fancied competency, ſome of the inſtructed though wealthy perhaps, ſhall be exempted from the Apoſtles iniunction: for ſuppoſe ſome one or two of the well diſpoſed hearers, ſhall out of their privat, make a competent allowance; the reſt ſhall now reap our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall things, and not ſow their carnall. For as the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is rife, enough in a miniſters maintenance, <hi>Enough is a feaſt:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 6.6.</note> but ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Let him .i.</hi> every him that is inſtructed, <hi>make his inſtructer partaker of all his goodes</hi> 2. See concluſion ſixt; &amp; duly weighing it, tell me whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou find conſcience ſatisfied with this imaginary competency? For is there no certaine proviſion for Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpell, but this vncertaine competency? who ſhall iudge of it? Every man? <hi>mallem Cerberum me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tueres,</hi> as the Orator ſpeakes. The Magiſtrat? why would not the Lord leaue this to Iewiſh Magiſtrats? no not to <hi>Moſes,</hi> a man ſo gratious with him? and leaue it to magiſtrats vnder the Goſpell? 3. How hath he commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this to Magiſtrats? abſolutely or with limitation? if with limits, what are theſe bounds? forſooth a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petency. Perceaue you not circling and meere vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainties?</p>
            <p>Leaue we this fancy, and ſee whether wee may find ſome other more certaine particular, to reſolue of. And ſurely when wee haue in vaine turmoiled our ſelues to avoid Iudaizing in this point of miniſters maintenance, we ſhall be forced at length to acknowledge Tenthes,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17338:6"/> which ſome call Jewiſh, to be the Miniſters appointed portion.</p>
            <p>That the truth may the better appeare, J will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound the different opinions that J haue met withal in this point.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Browniſts in this queſtion thus peremptorily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue. That Tithes are ſo meerely ceremonious and Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viticall, that they cannot without betraying Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal liberty and diſavowing Chriſts Prieſthood, be retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as maintenance of Miniſters of the Goſpell. And how full ſoever of dotage this dreame may ſeeme: yet this J will ſay for them; They are madd with more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon a great deale, then any others which hold them ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies Levitical. Jf the aſſumption were true, their concluſion woulde ſoundly followe by doctrine of the Apoſtle. <hi>Gal. 4. &amp; 5. Col.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 Some others thinking them iudicials, reſolue; part, that they may be lawfully retained as the Miniſters ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend; part, that they are the moſt convenient mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance can be allotted vs.</p>
            <p n="3">3 A third ſort, that they are due by Gods law to Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpell; but theſe in explanation of them ſelues diverſly deriue them thence.</p>
            <p n="1">1. ſome thus: due by Gods law enioyning obedience to the magiſtrate in things lawfull and convenient. Theſe giue them no other ground in Gods word, then other humane ordinances.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Others, due by Gods law: in as much as the church (whoſe authoritie with them is divine) hath enioined their payment. So generally Papiſts.</p>
            <p n="3">3 A third ſort thus: due by Gods lawe; in reſpect of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17338:7"/> their conſecration to God, either by receaued cuſtome and conſent of Churches, or by donation of princes, or legacie of teſtatours. In which opinion I muſt needes profeſſe my ſelfe to haue beene long; and never to my knowledge of other; til of late being to deliver my iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to my people, J more purpoſely ſet my ſelfe to ſee what the truth was. And during that miſtake, I thus thought; that they could not without ſacrilege be alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated from their general end<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> my reaſons were theſe, 1 That J had found <hi>Salomon</hi> averring it to bee <hi>a</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Pro. 20.25.</note> 
               <hi>curſe to devoure holy things, and had ſeene the curſe exemplified on many.</hi> 2. That ordinance of the Lord J held morall &amp; perpetuall,<note n="r" place="margin">Levit. 27, 18, 19.</note> 
               <hi>Nothing ſeparate from common vſe, no not of thoſe which man had ſeparated, might be againe vnhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, no nor redeemed.</hi> 3. That ſaying of the Apoſtle much ſwaied with me,<note n="ſ" place="margin">Gal. 3.15.</note> 
               <hi>If it bee but a mans teſtament no man abrogats it .i.</hi> no man ought to abrogate it. And ſo much the more, for that being once an auditour of that iudicious divine M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Perkins,</hi> whoſe memory is bleſſed; J heard him moue the doubt, whether things given to ſuperſtitious vſes, ſuppoſe to maintaine malmonging, might be alienated. And thus aſſoile to my reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance. That from the particular intention, wherein through ignorance they erred, alienation might be; but fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the generall ende, maintenance of Godes worſhip, they might not be aliened. Thus then &amp; vpon theſe grounds my concluſion is ſtill the ſame, though my <hi>media</hi> bee other, and ſomething more peremptory. Now becauſe it is a labour long and needleſſe to diſcuſſe every of the former differences (for the ſaying is true, <hi>verum eſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dex ſui &amp; obliqui:</hi>) J will firſt propound the concluſion
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17338:7"/> with the explanation; 2. Proceed to confirmation; And laſtly annex ſolution of Arguments, ſuch as J haue met withall, having any ſhew of ground from the word of God, to overthrowe the concluſion.</p>
            <p>The Concluſion in few words is this. <hi>Tithes are the portion, at leaſt part of that portion, by Gods word allotted to Miniſters for their ſervice in the goſpell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By Tithes vnderſtande the tenth part of all the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers increaſe:<note n="t" place="margin">Pro. 3 9.</note> particulars may be read, <hi>Levit. 27.30. &amp; alibi.</hi> In a word to vſe the diſtinction of Canoniſts, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be perſonall, of induſtry, negotiation; &amp;c. or prediall, as of grounds, &amp;c. or mixt, as of cattell: the tenthes of the whole encreaſe, not thoſe of Cumin &amp; Aniſe excepted<note n="u" place="margin">Mat. 23.23.</note>, fal within compaſſe of our ſubiect.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Of Tithes amongſt Iews we may finde fowre ſorts diſtinguiſhed by their ends. 1. ſome, which for diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſake, we may call ſtipendary, aſſigned to Levits for recompence of their ſervice. <hi>Numb. 18.24.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 A ſecond ſort which wee may call ſacrificatory: Tithes for ſacrifice. Some cal them <hi>Decimas ſecu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>daneas,</hi> ſome <hi>Decimas decimarum:</hi> a tithe of the Levits Tithes to be given to <hi>Aaron,</hi> as an heaue offring vnto the Lord. <hi>Numb. 18.28.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 A third kinde you may ſtile <hi>Convivales,</hi> banquet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or feaſting tithes, appointed for ſolemne feaſtes at their generall aſſemblies to Ieruſalem, <hi>Deut. 14.22, 23.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 The laſt ſort may be tearmed <hi>Eleemoſynariae.</hi> Some call them <hi>decimas pauperum,</hi> a tithe which for reliefe of the poore, widdowes, ſtrangers, &amp;c. were every thirde yeare to be ſet out of their goods, ever and aboue the other annuall tithes, <hi>Deut. 24.29.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:17338:8"/>
            <p>This diſtinction of tithes I thought good to mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of the Leviticall law: though this I profeſſe, not to claime our tithes by the mandate given in lawe Leviti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call.</p>
            <p>Now our queſtion is, only of thoſe tithes which we called ſtipendary; the reſt being two ſortes of them ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parently ceremonious; the third as plainly a iudicial or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance. And of thoſe tithes ſtipendary, this is that we affirme, that by the word of God they belong for ever to Miniſters of holy things, and therefore in theſe daies to Miniſters of the goſpell, who alone haue now to do with publike miniſtrations of the worſhip of God.</p>
            <p>Our reaſons are theſe: firſt grounded on <hi>Heb. 7.6.8. He whoſe deſcent is not cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted from them, receaved tithes of Abraham; and ver. 8. here men that die receiue tithes, but there he receaveth them of whom it is witneſſed that hee li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth. Compare Gen. 14.20.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The argument which this ſcripture affordeth, hath received much diſadvantage, by ſlender collection of many, thus only preſſing it; Tithes were paid to Prieſts before the Levitical law was given: therefore their pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded rather on morall then ceremoniall law. To which, anſwere is well given, that by as good infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, ſacrificing of beaſts may be proved a morality, ſith it alſo was in vſe before giving of the law by <hi>Moſes.</hi> That we may the better ſee the force of the Argument here given, let vs a little conſider the frame and ſumme of the text.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle by occaſion of the peoples dulnes, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving digreſſed from <hi>cap. 5.11.</hi> to <hi>cap. 6.20.</hi> returnes now to his purpoſe; namely to ſhew the excellencie of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17338:8"/> Chriſts prieſthood aboue that of <hi>Aaron,</hi> by avouching him a Prieſt after th'order of <hi>Melchiſedec.</hi> The concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is this: Chriſts prieſthood is more excellent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that of <hi>Levi;</hi> or Chriſt is a greater Prieſt then any after <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons</hi> order. The reaſon principall lyeth thus; He that is a Prieſt after the order of <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> is a greater Prieſt then the Prieſts after <hi>Aaron.</hi> But Chriſt is a Prieſt after the order of <hi>Melchiſedec, Ergo, &amp;c.</hi> The minor hath firſt his proofe, 1. from a teſtimony of <hi>David, cap. 5.20.</hi> 2. fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that abſolute agreement betwixt <hi>Melchiſedec,</hi> &amp; Chriſt: the partes whereof are theſe; 1. as <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> was king and Prieſt of the moſt high God, ſo Chriſt; 2. as <hi>Melchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedec</hi> king of righteouſnes and prince of peace, ſo Chriſt. 3. as <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> his parents, kindred, beginning, and end of life are not recorded: ſo Chriſt, as man, with out father; as God, without mother, kindred, begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, or end of life. Therefore Chriſt is truely a Prieſt after the order of <hi>Melchiſedec. ver. 1.2.3.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The maior remaines to be proved and that hath his proofe from <hi>ver. 4.</hi> to <hi>11.</hi> the ſumme whereof is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed in this principall ſyllogiſme. If <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> be greater then <hi>Levi,</hi> then he that is a Prieſt after his order as Chriſt is; is greater the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Levi.</hi> But <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then <hi>Levi. Ergo, &amp;c.</hi> minor proved, greater then <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> greater then <hi>Levi. Melchiſedec</hi> is greater then <hi>Abraham. Ergo</hi> then <hi>Levi.</hi> minor proved: he to whom <hi>Abraham</hi> paid tithes, of whom he was bleſſed, is greater then <hi>Abraham.</hi> But to <hi>Melchiſedec Abraham</hi> paid tithes, &amp; <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> bleſſed <hi>Abraham. Ergo</hi> is greater then hee, <hi>ver. 4.5.6.7.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſecond argument proving the greatneſſe of this
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17338:9"/> Prieſt aboue thoſe of <hi>Aarons</hi> order, is laid down, <hi>ver. 8.</hi> A tithe taker .i. Prieſt, of whom its teſtified that he liues, is greater the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a tithe taker that dyeth. But the Prieſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Milchiſedec</hi> is a tithe taker of whom its teſtified that he liveth; Levits take tithes and die. <hi>Ergo</hi> the Prieſt after <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> his order is greater then the Prieſts Leviti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call. This is in my ſimple Logique the diſpoſition of the text. As for illuſtrations or amplifications by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyllogiſmes, prolepſes, or otherwiſe, I purpoſely omit them Now me thinks, the text thus naturally reſolved, there needs no farther deduction of the Argument; yet that the ſimpleſt may ſee what footing tithes haue here thus I collect it.</p>
            <p>The portion due to Chriſts prieſthood, is due to Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the goſpell: but tithes are the portion due to Chriſts prieſthood. <hi>Ergo.</hi> The minor is thus proved.</p>
            <p>The portion due to <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> his prieſthood, is due to Chriſts prieſthood; reaſon, 1. for that Chriſts Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood and <hi>Melchiſedecs</hi> are the ſame; or Chriſt is a Prieſt after that order: 2. other things enunciated of <hi>Melchiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dec,</hi> are true of Chriſt eminently and alwaies: as its emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently and alwaies true of Chriſt, that he is king of righ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teouſnes and prince of peace; eminently and alwaies true of Chriſt, he is without pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, without beginning and end of life, that he bleſſeth <hi>Abraham</hi> and al his ſeed, &amp;c. All theſe are more properly verified of Chriſt then of <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> his type. Why not then alſo this ever true of him; he taketh tithes?</p>
            <p>Now I aſſume. But tithes are the portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> due to <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedec</hi> his prieſthood, yea ever due to that Prieſthood. For 1 they were paid by <hi>Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> to <hi>Melchiſedec,</hi> 2. in the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17338:9"/> Apoſtles Logicke; a Prieſt and receiver of tithes are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quipollents. In ſteed of ſaying men that die are Prieſts; he ſaith, <hi>men that die receiue tithes:</hi> in ſteed of ſaying <hi>hee that liues is a Prieſt;</hi> he ſaith, <hi>he that liues takes tithes:</hi> as if in his iudgement tithes and prieſthood were as inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable as kingdome and tribute.</p>
            <p>Now the maior of the principall ſyllogiſme if any doubt of, to wit, whether the portion due to Chriſt be due to Miniſters, let him compare <hi>1. Cor. 9 14.</hi> where is the expreſſe ordinance of Chriſt, that Miniſters ſhould liue of the Goſpell; 2. who in likelihood ſhould bee his receavers, but theſe that are in his ſtead, as its ſaid of Miniſters, <hi>2, Cor. 5.20?</hi> 3. Beſides the ſame reaſon which the Lord aſſignes of <hi>Levi</hi> his ſharing in things to him ſelfe reſerved and ſanctified, is true of Miniſters, or elſe of none.<note n="x" place="margin">Deut. 10, 8.9</note> 
               <hi>God is Levits portion .i.</hi> Gods portion is Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vits portion, becauſe they were taken to Miniſter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him. Why not then alſo Chriſts portion Miniſters portion, becauſe they only are aſſumed to Chriſt to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter in the Goſpell? A reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for not tithing of ſo plain deduction out of Scripture, if any can bring mee, hee ſhall much ſway me to his ſentence.</p>
            <p>This argument I remember once to haue propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſomething otherwiſe, to this purpoſe. The portion due to Prieſthood after <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> his order, is due to Miniſters of the Goſpell. But tithes are that portion. <hi>Ergo.</hi> And thus propounding it, I receaue theſe anſwers: the propoſition ſeemes vntrue, except you can proue your ſelues Prieſts after that order. <hi>Reſp.</hi> Wherto I thus anſwered; that though we be no Prieſts after that or let yet is there truth in the propoſition, ſith Chriſt the high
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:17338:10"/> Prieſt of our profeſſion to whome originally they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, hath ordained vs to liue of his portion.</p>
            <p>A ſecond anſwer was by limitation; the portion due (by law) to that Prieſthood is due to Miniſters. But with that limitation the aſſumption is falſe, <hi>Abrahams</hi> pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment being an act rather voluntary, then by any iniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction from God. But <hi>contra,</hi> that that act of <hi>Abraham</hi> was no act in this ſenſe voluntary, but rather an act of neceſſary and inioined duty, is evident (me thinkes) by theſe reaſons. 1. For that gifts voluntary proceeding from bountie or liberalitie, imply a ſuperioritie or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency in the giuer aboue the receaver. For<note n="y" place="margin">Act. 20.35.</note> 
               <hi>its a more bleſſed thing,</hi> in that kind, <hi>to giue then to receaue.</hi> But <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams</hi> paiment of tithes was teſtimony of his inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ority. Againe the phraſe it ſelfe<note n="z" place="margin">Heb. 7.4.6.</note> implies as much: <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedec tithed Abraham,</hi> ver. 6. a phraſe that looſeth all his emphaſis if no iniunction had ſubiected <hi>Abraham</hi> to a neceſſitie of being tithed. 3. What mean they whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſay of <hi>Abrahams</hi> tithing, that it was done without law? would they be vnderſtood of <hi>Abrahams</hi> fact onely, or of tithing at large as it was in vſe before the lawe written? Now ſure I wonder how firſt<note n="a" place="margin">Gen 14.20.</note> 
               <hi>Abraham,</hi> and then after him<note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 28.22</note> 
               <hi>Iacob,</hi> ſhould fall vpon a tenth rather then a ſixt or twelfth part, if there were nothing preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed in their times for tithing? 2. How proue they but probably that it was without iniunction of law? If this be the reaſon for that we finde no mention of any law to that end given: by as good reaſon may they ſay of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, and ſundry other actions religious, that they were arbitrary; ſith we finde no expreſſe mandate given of them in thoſe times. But thus mee thinkes wee may
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:17338:10"/> better reaſon from their practiſe to an iniunction; theſe facts of theirs were approved of God, therefore not done without iniunction from him. And of this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and cleering thereof thus farre.</p>
            <p>The ſecond argument hath his ground, <hi>Galat. 6.6. 1. Tim, 5.17. Prov. 3.9.</hi> where we read thus; <hi>Let him that is inſtructed, make his inſtructer partaker of all his goods; &amp; elders that rule well are worthie of double honour, eſpecially they that labour in the word and doctrine. And honour God with thy ſubſtance, and with the chiefe of all thine increaſe.</hi> Out of which Scriptures, thus we reaſon. If there bee a portion to be ſet out vnto God and his Miniſters, out of all and every the temporall goods of every one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed, and no certaine portion to bee found in ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures but tithes: then are tithes the portion allotted by Gods word to Miniſters for their ſervice. But there is a portion to be ſet out vnto God and his Miniſters out of the temporall goods of every one inſtructed, and no other certaintie mentioned in ſcripture but tithes. <hi>Ergo</hi> tithes are the portion allotted by Gods word to Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters for their ſervice.</p>
            <p>The conſequence of the propoſition depends vpon this ground, that ſome certaintie is by ſcripture allot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto Miniſters for their ſervice. Hereof if any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand proofe let him conſider theſe. Firſt, for that the Lord allotted a certaintie vnto firſt borne and Levits: &amp; thinke we it probable hee would leaue Miniſters of the Goſpell at randome to a competencie indeterminate? 2. Jn other caſes this argument goes current. The Lord preſcribes for the old Tabernacle all things neceſſarie even to the Beſome and Aſhpan; not a pin in the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:17338:11"/> but what hath his preſcript from God. Now ſurely of this we may ſay its not a pin, but even a <hi>Clavus Traba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is,</hi> one of the maſter nailes in our Tabernacle. And thinke we his word ſo ſufficient and abſolutely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act for all neceſſary preſcripts, yea circumſtances con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning worſhip, government, any thing: and this only, a matter of ſo great conſequence, left vnpreſcribed?</p>
            <p>Laſtly, if no certaintie in this kind can bee found in Scripture, how wilt thou be able to ſhare out vnto God his portion in faith? ſo that thou maiſt bee able to ſay, I haue giuen the Lord that portion of my goods which he requireth of me? Forſooth the Magiſtrats determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation ſhall in this point bee the levill and rule of faith. <hi>Reſp.</hi> 1. Then muſt thou bee able to ſhewe that the Lord hath made Magiſtrats in this point his Carvers, which is vnlikely <hi>vt ſupra:</hi> 2, Suppoſe Magiſtrats make no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, where is then the direction for thy faith? 3. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe they ſhall aſſigne <hi>Micah</hi> his allowance: wilt thou therewith be content? Then ſure al our lay perſons, our <hi>Micahs,</hi> haue faith well guided, conſciences rectified; <hi>ten ſhekels of ſilver,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Iudg. 17.10.</note> 
               <hi>and a meales meat, and livery,</hi> they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford <hi>Sir Iohn.</hi> In faith thinke wee? ſurely according to Magiſtrats proviſion. And why blame we any more, im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>propriat perſons for ſo ſca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t allowance? perhaps becauſe not competent. Yea but the Magiſtrate thinks it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent. And that is in this caſe the line of faith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>credam? non ſi mihi &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Touching the minor, for the firſt part ſee <hi>1. Cor. 9.11. Prov 3.9. Gal. 6.6.</hi> in which place yee haue it in ſo many termes. <hi>Let him that is inſtructed, make his inſtructer par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of all his goods.</hi> For the ſecond branch of it; that no
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:17338:11"/> other portion certaine is to bee founde in ſcripture; I meane which hath not an apparent ſignification of ſomething peculiar to that ſtate of the people vnder <hi>Levi,</hi> as firſt fruits, ſhare of other ſacrifices: wil appeare to any man, that wilbe pleaſed to enter induction of particulars. And may I not then conclude Tithes are the portion allotted vs by the word of God? Yea what if I ſhoulde ſay even tithes are in ſome of theſe places more then obliquely pointed at? What meanes the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle to call for maintenance vnto Miniſters vnder the terme of double honor?<note n="d" place="margin">1. Tim 5 17.18.</note> for that by honor he there meanes maintenance, the reaſon annexed will make a blinde man ſee. Surely <hi>S. Hierome</hi> having delivered his iudgement of that place, <hi>Mal. 3. Bring all my tithes into the ſtorehouſe,</hi> in theſe tearmes <hi>Eccleſiae populis praeceptum eſt dare decimas,</hi> alleageth preſently this place for proof, <hi>1. Tim. 5.17. Elders muſt haue double honor.</hi> Againe what meanes the Apoſtle by that Epithete (double) <hi>honour?</hi> ſay ſome, double <hi>.i.</hi> large and liberall; but why double ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then treble, if he meant large, at large? Doth he not rather in that Epithet ſend vs to conſider of that<note n="e" place="margin">Numb. 8.16.</note> 
               <hi>dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble portion of the firſt borne</hi> in whoſe roome <hi>Levi</hi> was aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed? And that which made their portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> double, was in part tithes, as ſhall hereafter at leaſt probably ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare vnto vs. Proceede we to a third reaſon which is grounded on <hi>Levit. 27.28. Prov. 20.25. Rom. 2.22. Mal. 3.8.</hi> where we read thus, <hi>Every thing ſeparate from common vſe, is moſt holy vnto the Lord.</hi> And <hi>it is a ſnare to devour holy things, &amp; after the vow to inquire.</hi> And <hi>thou which ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horreſt Idols, committeſt thou ſacrilege?</hi> And <hi>yee haue robbed me.</hi> Out of which places thus we reaſon. The portion
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:17338:12"/> which hath bin ſeparated from common vſe, to maine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of Gods worſhip vnder the new teſtament, is the portion allotted by the word of God to Miniſters for their ſervice.</p>
            <p>But tithes are the portion, at leaſt part of the portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeparate from common vſe to mainetenance of Gods worſhip vnder the new teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. <hi>Ergo</hi> &amp;c. The maior is thus proved; becauſe the detainement or alienating of things ſo conſecrated, is ſacrilege. That this may the better appeare, it wilbee worth the while to conſider briefly what ſacriledge is: which out of <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Zanchius Vrſine,</hi> and others, we may thus briefly deſcribe: <hi>Sacrilege</hi> is the taking away of things ſacred <hi>.i.</hi> deputed to holie vſes, or the maintenance of the worſhip of God. The matter about which this theft is converſant, are things conſecrated to God; of which there are two ſorts: ſome which God himſelfe either by reſervation, or expreſſe mandate, hath hallowed vnto himſelfe; ſome which man hath hallowed and ſeparated from common vſe. of both read <hi>Levit. 27.28.29.30.</hi> Now that which makes vp the nature of ſacrilege, is, the taking away or detai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of things thus hallowed, and returning them to common vſe. Thus then I reaſon, the detainement or alienating of any thing ſeparate from common vſe, is ſacrilege. But detainement or alienating of tithes, is the detainement and alienating of thinges thus ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate. <hi>Ergo</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the propoſition theſe anſwers I haue partly read, partly heard in conference. 1. Vnderſtand it ſay ſome of things which haue beene conſecrate by law. <hi>Reſp.</hi> 1. no word of God forceth to ſuch limitation. For even of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:17338:12"/> voluntary and votary conſecrations both <hi>Moſes, Levit. 27.</hi> and <hi>Salomon, Prov. 20.25.</hi> ſpeake. And was it not free to <hi>Ananias</hi> to conſecrate or not, more then generall lawes of piety or charity might ſway him, <hi>Act. 5.4.</hi> whiles it remained was it not thine owne? And after it was ſold was it <hi>not in thy power,</hi> ſaid <hi>Peter?</hi> yet was <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanias</hi> his detainement ſacrilege by circumſtances of the text and conſent of beſt interpreters. He is taxed by <hi>Peter</hi> not only for lying, but for theeviſh and clancular ſurreption of part of the price, <hi>ver. 3.</hi> and, ſaith <hi>Beza</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreting the word, <hi>Ad ſacrilegium etiam acceſſit deffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentia &amp; hypocriſis.</hi> ſee alſo <hi>Centuriat. Cent. 1. lib. 2. cap. 4. Ambroſ. ſer. 9. Dum ex eo quod promiſerat, partem ſubtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hit, ſacrilegij ſimul condemnatur &amp; fraudis. Sacrilegij quod Deum in pollicitatione fefellerit: fraudis quod, &amp;c:</hi> 2. but grant it with that limitation; wee ſhall anone ſee, that with that limit we may aſſume of tithes that they haue bin conſecrated.</p>
            <p>A ſecond reſtraint ſome haue thus given to the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; vnderſtand it ſay they, of alienating things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated without error <hi>.i.</hi> to maintenance of true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the true God. Well, agreed; let it be ſo limited, though with faire probability and conſent of no ſmall clarks, we might contend the contrary. <hi>Keckerman:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Syſt. Polit. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceps iure non poteſt res ſacras &amp; bona cultui divino etiam in genere deſtinata, etiam ea quae ſuperſtitioſo cultui ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt, in vſum profanum tranſferre.</hi> But grant the limitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: can we not aſſume thus much of Tithes, that they haue bin conſecrate to maintaine pure worſhip of the true God?</p>
            <p>Thirdly vnderſtand it ſay ſome, with theſe excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:17338:13"/> 1. Except in caſe of the churches ſuperfluity; &amp; this exception hath this ground; contentment with neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries is required of Miniſters; for <hi>Moſes</hi> cries <hi>ſufficit</hi> at the building of the tabernacle: <hi>Reſp.</hi> What word of God or ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d reaſon giues liberty to alien ſeeming ſuperflui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Miniſters rather then of other ſubiects? content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with neceſſaries being equally required of all. And <hi>Moſes</hi> ſtaies addition of more; returnes or aliens no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of what was brought by the people, no not though there were an overplus. But ſecondly grant the propoſition with that exception; in what caſe, in what times may we not with that limit aſſume of tithes?</p>
            <p>Their ſecond exception is when alienation is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for preſervation of the Church. <hi>Reſp.</hi> An vſe of ſuch goods for the time, may perhaps in that caſe bee allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: perpetuall alienation, beſides facts of ſome men, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing makes probable. The ſhew bread was made com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon to <hi>David</hi> &amp; his company in extremitie: but might it therefore be perpetually aliened, ſuch neceſſitie cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing?</p>
            <p>Their laſt exception, when Princes haue no other meanes to remunerate ſubiects, faithfull in common ſervices. <hi>Reſp.</hi> What, I wonder, in ſuch caſe laies open Church goods to the will of Princes, rather then the goods of common ſubiects? Thus I reaſon and leaue them: privat goods of ſubiects, Magiſtrats may not ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en from them for recompenſe of ſervants, much leſſe may the Lords portion bee transferred to ſuch vſes. See <hi>Gen. 47.22.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus then the propoſition is cleere as it was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded: let vs grant it with theſe limits or ſo many of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:17338:13"/> them as haue any ſhew of reaſon to ſupport them. And thus conclude. The detainment or alienating of things by law conſecrated to pure worſhip of the true God, without ſuperfluity, anie longer then neceſſitie requires is ſacrilege. But tithes haue been by law conſecrated to maintenance of pure worſhip of the true God, are not ſuperfluous, and now no ſuch neceſſitie of their aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Ergo</hi> their detainment is ſacrilege.</p>
            <p>The fourth reaſon followes. Whatſoever duty pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in the word of God not either ceremoniall or Iudiciall, that is vndoubtedly of perpetuall obſervation. But payment of tithes is a duty preſcribed in the worde of God, and is neither ceremoniall nor iudiciall. <hi>Ergo</hi> of perpetuall obſervation. The propoſition I thinke none will doubt of, ſith there is no duty preſcribed in the word of God which fals not vnder ſome member of this diſtribution, and only Iudicials &amp; ceremonies were temporary.</p>
            <p>See we therefore whether our aſſumption for both parts of the predicate may bee avowed. And firſt that this is no dutie ceremonious; theſe reaſons evince. 1. Ceremoniall ordinances were all ſhaddowes of things to come, the body whereof is Chriſt. This no ſhaddow of things to come, for where is the body which this ſhadowed? ſome, who yet will haue it no ceremony but a iudiciall, frame this ceremonious reſemblance. The number of ten is a number of perfection, and by paying in this number, as by a ſigne, the offerer makes proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his owne imperfection, &amp; of his expecting per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Chriſt. Prettie too too. Others thus, they were paid in ſigne of thankfulneſſe; others, <hi>in ſignum vniver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalis
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:17338:14"/> Dominij.</hi> Twentie ſuch like, a tolerable wit woulde deviſe: but can they ſhew vs theſe ſignifications or ends of payment in the Scripture, even but obſcurely ſo much as by alluſion intimated? J dare ſay no, nor any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther end, no not of their payment to Levits, but main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance and recompenſe for their ſervice.</p>
            <p n="2">2 All ceremonies haue an analogicall reſemblance of the things they ſignified. Therefore called<note n="f" place="margin">Col 2.17.</note> 
               <hi>ſhaddows of things to come,</hi> becauſe that as the ſhaddowe carries though a darke, yet ſome reſemblance of the body whoſe ſhadow it is; ſo ceremonies of Chriſt: therefore tearmed alſo<note n="g" place="margin">Heb. 9.23. Gal. 4 9.</note> ſimilitudes of heavenly things, being or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by their very ſemblances <hi>to teach the rude.</hi> This hath no Analogicall reſemblance either of imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or thankfulneſſe, or Gods vniverſall dominion. For who can, J ſay, not only avow his frame, but even frame it except abſurdly? Giue vs ſuch an analogy of this as we are able to ſhew of others, wee will then beleeue their payment, to haue beene levitically ceremonious. Of ſprinklings and purifyings, of Tabernacle, of Arke, of Propitiatory, of high Prieſt (and indeed of what not, that was truly a ſhaddow of heavenly things?) we finde their analogie in the word of God. For inſtance, as<note n="h" place="margin">Heb. 9.7.2.</note> 
               <hi>high Prieſt amongſt the Iewes alone entered into the holy of holies not without bloud:</hi> ſo Chriſt into heaven, &amp;c. Can thoſe that ſo confidently avow tithes to haue been ceremonies, thus drawe out the ſimilitude betwixt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and heavenly things?</p>
            <p n="3">3 Whatſoever ordinance was before leviticall lawe, not foreſhadowing Chriſt, that is no ceremonie. But payment of tithes ſuch.<note n="i" place="margin">Heb. 14 &amp; 28 &amp; Col. 2 Heb. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.7. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Ergo.</hi> No leviticall ceremony
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:17338:14"/> may be vſed after publiſhing of the Goſpel.<note place="margin">Reclamante mundo, libera voce pronuncio ceremonias Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daeorum &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitioſas eſſe, &amp; mortiferas chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianis. Hierom. epiſt. Auguſt. <hi>11<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> (The ſchool men ſay well, <hi>Iudicialia poſt Chriſtum</hi> be <hi>mortua,</hi> becauſe they bind not: <hi>ceremonialia, mortifera;</hi> their very revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving vnlawfull and deadly.) But payment of tithes, by conſent of all, except Browniſts, may be retained. <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5 J finde not that the Lord in propheticall ſcriptures taxeth ſo much the omiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ceremonies, or exacteth in ſo ſtrict tearmes their performance, as hee doth this of tithes<note n="k" place="margin">Mal. 3 9.</note>. Something J finde of their faultie perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance; ſomething, of their ſticking in them with neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of moralities: and this to me is a preſumptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they were other then ceremonies.</p>
            <p>Laſtly J never read Chriſt ſpeak ſo much of any Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh ceremonie, as he did of tithes;<note n="l" place="margin">Mat. 23.</note> 
               <hi>theſe things ought you to haue done.</hi> Though J confeſſe, as much might haue beene ſaid of ceremonies during thoſe times. All theſe conſidered, may J not conclude of tithing, it was no ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonie? See wee whether perhaps it were a iudiciall, concerning only the nation of the Iewes, and founded on equitie particular to that people. This is indeed the olde tenent of Papiſts. But 1. ſay ſome, Judicials were all of duties from man to man. This ordinance of holy things to be done to God. Therefore not iudiciall.</p>
            <p>But what, trow we, imagine Papiſts to bee the civill equitie of this ordinance, particularly concerning the nation of the Jewes? Forſooth ſaith <hi>Bellarmine</hi> out of <hi>Thomas,</hi> the tribe of <hi>Leui</hi> being but the tenth, or at moſt the twelfth or thirteenth part of the Jews: tenths muſt be theirs that equitie may be kept, and that tribe haue no greater portion then the reſt. <hi>Reſp.</hi> 1. But it is wel an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered that this end of their aſſignement to <hi>Levi,</hi> hath
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:17338:15"/> no mention in Scripture: they are given to <hi>Levi</hi> for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence of this ſervice, as the Lords portion prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, other end or reaſon of their aſſignation wee finde none. 2. If this were the ende of their allotment to <hi>Leui:</hi> ſurely the Lord much forgat himſelfe, that beſides the tenthes of all mens goods, would allot them ſhare in ſacrifices and vowes, and 48 Citties with Suburbes of ſo large circuit as we read, <hi>Numb. 35.4.7.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 Be it granted, that this was ſome reaſon of their aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignement to <hi>Levi:</hi> how concludes this the ordinance in generall? For the iniunction of tithing was as old as <hi>Abraham</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Gen 14.20.</note>, when was no place for partition of Gods people by tribes. And if this be all they haue to proue them iudicials. J ſhall craue pardon for ſubſcribing to their iudgement. Laſtly, yeeld them Judicials: yet if of common equitie, if confirmed by poſitiue law, if con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting with law of nature, if ſerving to vphold morall duties; binds not the ordinance for ever? J conclude therefore, ſith neither ceremoniall nor iudiciall, or if iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall, yet of commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> equitie: therefore their payment is perpetually to be obſerved.</p>
            <p>The laſt reaſon (for I had rather giue reaſons by weight then number) is taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> practiſe of the church in all times fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beginning of the world downe to theſe laſt daies of reformation: ever ſince God had a miniſtry in the world, tithes were their maintenance. Before the law, the firſt borne; then, the ordinary prieſts, received tithes.<note n="m" place="margin">Gen. 14.20</note> For that, that <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> was <hi>She<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Noahs</hi> eldeſt ſon, at leaſt by priviledge, if not by birth, few queſtion, none diſproue: for the time vnder the law, is no queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For Apoſtles times or much of them, the vſe of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:17338:15"/> tithes, perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or ſcandale forced to be intermitted. Yet continued that <hi>Ius</hi> ever in them, and their inferior Presbyters. And therefore they vrge yeelding of main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, ſuch no doubt in their generall aime as was certaine by the word of God; ſuch as had bin in vſe: yea plead for portion<note n="n" place="margin">Gal. 6 6. 1. Tim. 5.17.</note> of al goods; for double honour. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter when God was pleaſed to graunt even but a little reſt, &amp; breathing time to the Churches, preſently came tithes againe to be the Miniſters portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Cyprian</hi> whoſe martyrdome fel into the yeare of the Lord 259. accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Euſebius</hi> his computatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Epiſt. 66.</note> amongſt other goods of the church, more then intimats tithes to haue bin co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mitted to Biſhops as generall ſtewards by whom they were diſtributed to inferiour Miniſters. Vpon occaſion taxing <hi>Geminius Victor</hi> for appointing <hi>Geminius Fauſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> a presbyter, overſeer of his will, and thereby occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning diſtraction from his miniſtery, ſets down by way of aggravation the courſe eſtabliſhed in the Church of God for preventing ſuch diſtractions in the miniſtry. As by Gods owne authority and diſpoſition, the tribe of <hi>Levi</hi> received tithes from the other tribes, &amp;c. that they might by no meanes be called away, or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrained to thinke or deale with things ſecular: the ſame courſe and order is now holden in the Church, <hi>Vt qui in Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia Domini ordinatione clerica promoventur, in nullo ab ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtratione divina avocentur, nec moleſtijs &amp; negotijs ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularibus alligentur, ſed in honore ſportulantium fratrum tanquam decimas ex fructibus accipientes, ab altari &amp; ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificijs non recedant, ſed die ac nocte caeleſtibus rebus &amp; ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualibus ſerviant<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> this mentions <hi>Cyprian</hi> as a courſe in his time received in the Church. In the ſame age a few
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:17338:16"/> yeares after was <hi>Dionyſius</hi> biſhop of Rome about the yeare 266.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 10.</note> This man (as <hi>Platina</hi> in his life teſtifieth; and as himſelfe of himſelfe, in his epiſtle to <hi>Severus,</hi>) aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſeverall Churches to ſeverall Miniſters, as pariſhes, leaſt one Paſtor might defraud another:<note place="margin">Gratian cauſ. <hi>13.</hi> q. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> the queſtion being then, not whether to any, but vnto what church, tithes were to be paid. The concluſion extant at large in the body of the Canon law, with ſome reaſons (both moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſonant to his decree;) it will not be amiſſe brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to collect; becauſe it is of ſome vſe in this matter of tithes. That which is proved there, is, that tithes are payable to the baptiſmall Churches, and to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters there ſerving God, and miniſtring to the people. After many teſtimonies heaped vp togither, <hi>Gal. 6.6. 1. Cor. 9.</hi> at length it is concluded with this expoſtulation; <hi>Quis plantat vineam, &amp;c.</hi> who plants a vineyard, &amp; eats not of the fruit thereof? <hi>Nos plantavimus vineam, &amp; vos vultis edere? Item praecepit Dominus per Moſem, vt nemo mittat falcem in alienam meſſem. Haec meſſis noſtra eſt, &amp; vos vultis falcem in eam mittere? Item Apoſtolus, they that ſerue at the altar liue of the altar; ſed numquid de eo cui no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſerviunt? Qui in ſacrario operantur, cum ſacrario partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pant; ſed numquid cum illo in quo non operantur? &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That I may not ſpend time &amp; paper whiles I doe but <hi>actum agere:</hi> for the next age, read what <hi>Hierome</hi> hath touching practiſe of the Church, in his epiſtle to <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potian; Ambroſe</hi> his iudgement in <hi>ſer. quadrageſ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In times ſucceeding, <hi>Chryſoſt. hom. 18.</hi> in <hi>Act. Auguſt.</hi> in <hi>Pſal. 146. &amp;c:</hi> calling for tithes, and ſharply reproving their detainment or ſpare payment. For Councils, that one Synode called <hi>Matiſconenſis</hi> held <hi>anno 580;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uriat.</note> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:17338:16"/> holden at that citty, <hi>Can. 5.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cent.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 9.</note> not only ordaines their payment, but ſheweth the obſervation of that duety to haue bin of long ſtanding in the Chriſtian Church. <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges divinae conſulentes ſacerdotibus ac miniſtris eccleſiarum pro haereditaria portione, omni populo praeceperunt, decimas fructuum ſuorum locis ſacris praeſtare, vt nullo labore impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diti, per res illegitimas, ſpiritualibus poſſint vacare mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterijs. Quas lege. Chriſtianorum congeries longis tempori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus cuſtodivit, intemeratas: nunc autem paulatim praevari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catores legum, poene Chriſtiani omnes oſtenduntur, dum ea quae divinitus ſancita ſunt, adimplere negligunt. Vnde ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuimus ac decernimus, vt mos antiquus à fidelibus repare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp; decimas eccleſiaſticis famulantibus ceremonijs popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus omnis inferat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this ſay the Century writers out of <hi>Aventine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cent. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi> de bonis Eccl.</note> 
               <hi>lib. 3. Annal decimas à profanis occupatas Carolomannus ſuo edicto reſtitui iubet.</hi> Tithes vſurped by ſeculars, or (as perhaps he names them for their fact) profane per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, <hi>Charlemaine</hi> by his edict comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds to be reſtored. The ſame authors out of <hi>Crantzius</hi> his metropolis, <hi>lib. 1. cap. 8. talem ſtatum Carolus magnus, poſt impoſitum iugu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſti reliquit in provincia, vt liber eſſet populus à tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum iugo, caeterum Eccleſijs &amp; pontificibus iure decimaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> obnoxius permaneret.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To leaue forrenners, in England <hi>Anno Dom. 786.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cent.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 9.</note> after accompt of theſe writers, was holden a Synode of all ſtates of the kingdomes and the decrees therof ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, by the ſeverall kings then raigning; and their aſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, Biſhops, Dukes, and Cominaltie. In the 17 chapter of which Council thus we read. <hi>De Decimis dandis, ſicut in lege ſcriptum eſt, decimam partem ex omnibus frugibus
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:17338:17"/> tuis ſeu primitijs deferas in domum domini dei tui: rurſum per prophetam: adferte, inquit, omnem decimam in horreum meum, vt ſit cibus in domo mea; et probate me ſuper hoc, &amp;c dicit dominus: ſicut ſapiens ait, nemo iuſtam Eleemoſynam de his quae poſsidet facere valet, niſi prius ſeparaverit domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no, quod à primordio ipſe ſibi reddere delegauit: ac per hoc plerun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> contingit, ut qui decimam non tribuit, ad decimam revertatur. Vnde etiam cum obtestatione praecipimus, vt omnes ſtudeant, de omnibus quae poſſide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, decimas dare, quia ſpeciale domini dei ſui eſt: &amp; de novem partibus ſibi vivat, &amp; Eleemoſynas tribuat.</hi> More need not be added. How in after times the caſe of tithes ſtood amongſt vs, practiſe of the Church in this land till the daies of <hi>Henry</hi> the 8, abundantly witneſſeth: exorbitancie enough from the primary rule of aſſignement to pariſh Churches might be noted; but till thoſe daies nothing is found of their whole alienation to ſeculars.</p>
            <p>As a corollary here let vs obſerue that tithes of Eng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>land haue bin by law ſeparate from common vſe: the inference thence is out of former grounds, that they could never be lawfully alienated. Yes ſaid one once; for <hi>eius eſt tollere, cuius ponere. Reſp. Peter</hi> was not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with any ſuch mixime in the caſe of <hi>Ananias;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Syſt Polit. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>Levit. 27. Things once ſeparated from common vſe, are forever holy vnto the Lord.</hi> And heare <hi>Keckerman, Princeps iure non poteſt &amp;c. Things ſacred or goods deſigned, or deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to diuine worſhip, though but in a generality, yea though they ſerue to ſuperſtitious worſhip, Princes haue no right to transfer to common vſe.</hi> Jf his ſentence ſwaie nothing, heare his reaſon: <hi>Res ſacrae pertinent ad ſtatum &amp; ſcopum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eipub. eminentiorem &amp; perfectiorem, ideo ad inferiorem
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17338:17"/> retrahi non debent. media enim perfectiorem finem reſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia, non debent abuſive ad imperfectiorem applicari.</hi> And <hi>Polanus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Ezec. c. 48. verſ. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Res ſanctas è quarum numero eſt poſſeſsio Deo ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctificata, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vendat, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> permutet, neque transferat quiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam. Ratio legi addita eſt; quia res ſanctae non ſunt homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, ſed ipſius Iehovae, cui dicatae, cui conſecratae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſt. 33.</note> 
               <hi>cui ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficatae ſunt &amp;c. Ambroſe</hi> when one thus preſſeth him to deliver vp the Temple to the Emperour; becauſe all things were his: thus anſwers; <hi>Noli te gravare Impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, vt putes te in ea quae divina ſunt imperiale aliquid ius habere; noli te extollere: ſed ſi vis diutius imperare, eſto Deo ſubditus: ſcriptum eſt; quae Dei Deo, quae Caeſaris Caeſari.</hi> But enough of this<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> we haue ſeen the practiſe of the church in all times, and ſo their iudgement for this duty of ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; which alone, ſo long, ſo generally, on ſuch grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds continued, me thinkes proues more for their paiment, then any preſcription though never ſo gray headed, or even bald with age, can for their detainement.</p>
            <p>J might ad to this continual practiſe of the Church, the vnanimous conſent of divines in iudgement, from Apoſtles daies downeward; till ſuch time as Popiſh Demi-ſacrilege had made ſeiſure of tithes, transferring them from parochial Paſtors to the Cove<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of Drones: then began their Schoolemen to ſtudie ſhifts, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to iuſtifie the practiſe of their <hi>Synagogue,</hi> and after many diſputs, reſolved of this as beſt plaſter for that ſore, that forſooth they were Judicials. I might alſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioine the conſenting practiſe of heathen by light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, yea ſuffrages of ſundry late divines; but that this taske is ſufficiently done by others; and authorities of men even beſt learned and devouteſt, beare little ſway
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:17338:18"/> in truthes ſo dangerous. This only I deſire, that in this queſtion we may contend with reaſons, rather then au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thorities: not that J feare to bee overlaid either with waight or number of voices; for the ods in both kindes I dare avow to be with vs. But 1. whereto tends com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting of divines in fight, except to worke diſtraction in people? And, 2. the ſaying of <hi>Auguſtine</hi> is me thinkes iudicious; <hi>Scripturarum autoritatibus, non quorumque proprijs, ſed vtriſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> communibus teſtibus, res cum re, cauſa cum cauſa, ratio cum ratione concertet.</hi> And of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving part hetherto.</p>
            <p>Let vs now proceed to examine ſuch arguments as are brought by the adverſe part to diſproue this truth; ſuch J meane as ſeeme to haue any footing in the word of God. For other, others haue fully and often anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them. Thus then ſome reaſon. Tithes are not in all the new Teſtament ſpecified to bee the miniſters main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance; ſo indeed reaſons <hi>Bellarmine;</hi> ſo <hi>Thomas,</hi> ſo <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſius</hi> and many others of that rancke of honeſt men. <hi>In nova lege,</hi> in the new law <hi>.i.</hi> in ſcriptures of the newe Teſtament we finde no ſuch precept, <hi>Ergo</hi> not due to Miniſters by the word of God. <hi>Reſp.</hi> Now ſure J had thought it had beene ſufficient to haue found them grounded on any part of Scripture not particularly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Church of the Iewes, becauſe<note n="o" place="margin">1. Tim 3.16.</note> 
               <hi>the whole Scripture is given by inſpiration from God; and</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">2. Pet. 1.19.</note> 
               <hi>that word of Prophets</hi> (ſaith <hi>Peter) is a moſt ſure word, we ſhall doe well to attend thereto.</hi> And therefore hetherto it hath been a maxime amongſt divines; <hi>A parte ſcripturae non valet ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentum negativè.</hi> Jts a morall ſtatute given to Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrats to puniſh with death,<note n="q" place="margin">Gen. 9.6.</note> 
               <hi>the ſhedder of mans blood;</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:17338:18"/> yet J finde it not ſpecified in all the new Teſtament: An ordinance irrevocable that the Sabboth bee kept with ceſſation from labours; yet ſpecification of the dutie J finde not in the new Teſtament. Sundry the like might be inſtanced, as by view of that place <hi>Ezek. 22 7. ad 12.</hi> to every man may appeare. Only let mee intreat men fearing God, not ſo farre to forget their reverence to the old ſcriptures, and the ſpirit that inſpired them, as to deny the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their ſhare with the new Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; of being rule in part of their faith and practiſe. This age is ſtrangely in loue with Epitomees, if faith it ſelfe ſhall be drawne to her compendium;<note place="margin">Aug. de bono perfect. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> But let vs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware we fall not into Manicheiſme. Chriſt ſaid of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Ioh. 5.45.</note> 
               <hi>He ſhould iudge the Iewes,</hi> ſo ſhall hee and Prophets iudge Chriſtians alſo, as well as Evangeliſts and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Who can queſtion this truth ſo cleare to all men? ſo neceſſary for all that will with <hi>Tertullian</hi> maintaine the fulneſſe of the Scriptures? That <hi>ſcripture teacheth as well what it implies, as what it expreſſeth.</hi> Teacheth it not particulars in generals? Effects or conſequents in prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples? equals by equivalence? The concluſion is not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in ſcriptures of the new Teſtament; that precept of Sabboth is not abrogated: yet taught in the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament. Sith<note n="ſ" place="margin">Mat. 5.17.</note> no precept of the Decalogue abrogated; <hi>Ergo</hi> not that of <hi>Sabboth.</hi> The concluſion not expreſſed in the new Teſtament; <hi>Infants are to bee baptiſed,</hi> yet taught in the new Teſtament:<note n="t" place="margin">Act. 2.38.39 Mar. 10.14. 1. Cor. 7.14. Act 10.47.</note> 
               <hi>ſith to whome promiſes, kingdome, covenant, ſpirit belong,</hi> to them baptiſme. <hi>Ergo</hi> to infants. Theſe doctrines are all taught in the newe Teſtament, becauſe generals, principles, or equivalents
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:17338:19"/> are there taught. And ſo haue wee tithes preſcribed in the new Teſtament, <hi>vt ſupra.</hi> Yea more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo <hi>implicite;</hi> as in former reaſons hath already appeared. Its by this occaſion nowe in my minde that <hi>Tertullian</hi> hath in his treatie <hi>de ſpectaculis;</hi> where be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding himſelfe to diſſwade Chriſtians from preſence at ſuch prophane and barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſpectacles as were then in vſe, hee thus ſhapes an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to a reaſon of this mould: <hi>Quorundam fides</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>aut ſimplicior, aut ſcrupuloſior, ab hac abdicatione ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>culorum de ſcripturis autoritatem expoſcit, &amp; ſe in incer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum conſtituit, quod non ſignificanter ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> nominatim de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuncietur ſervis Dei abſtinentia eiuſmodi:</hi> Some mens faith (ſaith <hi>Tertullian</hi>) whether over ſimple, or over ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous, demaundes our authoritie from ſcriptures for this abandoning ſuch ſights; and makes it ſelfe doubtful becauſe ſuch abſtinence is not there expreſly and by name inioined to the ſervants of God. Whereto he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers; <hi>planè nuſquam inuenimus, &amp;c.</hi> Its true, ſaith that autor, we finde not in any place, that as it is apertly ſaid, <hi>thou ſhalt not kill, &amp;c.</hi> ſo its expreſly defined, thou ſhalt not goe to the circle or Theater &amp;c. but wee finde that general of <hi>David</hi> to touch this particular; Bleſſed is hee that hath not walked in the counſell of the vngodly, nor ſtand in the way of ſinners; if in no way of ſinners, then not in this: <hi>Nam apud ſpectacula &amp; in via ſtatur, &amp;c.</hi> There needs no application.</p>
            <p>Now this argument the ſame for ſubſtance ſome haue vrged with this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; In ſcriptures of the newe Teſtament, where Miniſters maintenance is purpoſely treated of, no mention is to be found of tithes: And that is at leaſt a preſumption, their payment is no perpetual
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:17338:19"/> ordinance of God. For is it likely the particular would haue beene concealed? <hi>Reſp.</hi> Perhaps, and but perhaps not; 1 If either ſtate of the times had borne it, or 2. ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie required, or 3. Apoſtles had beene willing to vrge the vttermoſt of right. But conſidering firſt the diſtreſſe of the times, was ſuch, as ſcarce any could call any thing his owne; 2. weighing againe how fully the particular was in the old Teſtament determined; laſtly pondering how loth the Apoſtles were, to exact right, leaſt any occaſion ſhould be given, to ſuſpect of merce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary or covetous affection in preaching: it was as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient to omit particularizing the quantitie, as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the vſe of all right, as to ſome Churches ſome pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed.</p>
            <p n="2">2 But yet this J finde; they call for<note n="u" place="margin">1. Tim. 5.17.</note> double honour. For<note n="x" place="margin">1. Cor. 9.5. ad 14.</note> maintenance due by law of nature, and nations, and by ordinance of Chriſt, and that is either tithes, or elſe no certaine particular.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Who will vndertake to evidence the particulars of all duties of iuſtice, charity, temperance, even there where hee ſhall finde ſuch duties purpoſely preſcribed? Or be ſo bold <hi>(ne quid dicam gravius)</hi> as to exclude par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularities of theſe duties from intention of Gods ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit becauſe the generals are only handled, vpon ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed likelyhoods, or preſumptions truly preſumptuous? Leaue we therefore this argument, and ſee whither the reſt haue better colour. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> endevouring to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue the morality of this duty, thus reaſons; Moral du<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties haue ever bound conſcience, eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before the law of <hi>Moſes.</hi> But the lawe of tithes was not till the times of <hi>Moſes. Ergo. Reſp.</hi> the propoſition we acknowledge. The
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:17338:20"/> minor how will he proue? If hee ſhall reaſon from the ſcriptures ſilence; the ſame may be ſaid of adultery, Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, periury, almoſt of what not? 2. We haue that which is equivalent to a precept; the approved practiſe of the Saints of God; yea if <hi>Lyra</hi> may be credited, an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied precept given to <hi>Iacob, Gen. 35.1.</hi> when he is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to build an altar at <hi>Bethel</hi> according to his vow made, <hi>Gen. 28.</hi> Looke backe to what is ſaid in clearing the firſt Argument, and thereby iudge whither the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of tithing were in thoſe daies given, or not.</p>
            <p>His next reaſon is this, Reaſon naturall teacheth not the payment of tenthes to Prieſts, but only of what is ſufficient to their ſuſtentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Ergo</hi> not morall. <hi>Reſp.</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth reaſon direct to keeping a ſeaventh daie, but only a ſeparation of ſome ſolemne times to Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. But who would conſult with reaſon corrupted, &amp; blinde ſince the fall, to determine of moralities? Since al it reacheth vnto, even where it hath ſome helpe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall grace, are generalities only of morall duties?</p>
            <p>His laſt reaſon, Matters of vow are no moralities: tithes were<note n="y" place="margin">Gen. 28.22.</note> vowed by <hi>Iacob: Ergo</hi> not commaunded. <hi>Reſp.</hi> And are all matters of vow things arbitrary, none moralities? What thinke yee of that <hi>ver. 21.</hi> vttered in ſome vow, and as it were with the ſame breath of <hi>Iacob; If the Lord will go with me, and keepe mee in the way that I ſhall goe, &amp;c. then ſhall the Lord be my God?</hi> Was it a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Arbitrary to <hi>Iacob</hi> to haue the Lord, and him only to be his God? being the ſubſtance of the firſt morall precept? Yet was it vowed by <hi>Iacob,</hi> as we ſee, on like conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with tithes. More inſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces might be alleaged: but <hi>quorſum:</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:17338:20"/>
            <p>Proceede wee to argumentes of our owne divines. Tithes ſay ſome are originally in kings and civill Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, and its their Miſhpat. i. <hi>ius</hi> to diſpoſe of them to civill or religious vſe. For ſaith the Lord; of Iſraels king, <hi>Hoc erit ius regis veſtri, &amp;c:</hi> hee ſhall take tithes, <hi>1. Sam. 8.15. Reſp.</hi> Is it poſſible men ſhoulde adviſedly thus reaſon out of this ſcripture?<note n="z" place="margin">Levit. 27.30</note> The Lorde had long ere this declared tithes to be his,<note n="a" place="margin">Num. 18.24.</note> aſſigned the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to <hi>Levi</hi> for his ſervice in the tabernacle: and that vnder Magiſtrats civill though not kings. When in his wrath he giues a king to Iſrael, revoked he his ordinance of ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to <hi>Levi?</hi> Who can think it? I ſtand not to diſpute the queſtion, whether the words deſcribe a king, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a tyrant. But this I am ſure is evident: the Lorde there ſhewes the many miſchiefes ſhoulde befall them as a plague for their reiecting the government by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe eſtabliſhed, ſuch as ſhould make them cry vnder the burthen of his exaction. A courſe beſeeming an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orbitant tyrant, rather then a regular king. <hi>Iuſt:</hi> yea but this ſhalbe his Miſhpat. i. his <hi>ius ver. 11. Reſp.</hi> And why his <hi>ius</hi> rather then his guiſe? His right rather then his faſhion? As moſt render, and the word oft ſignifie. See <hi>1. Sam. 27.11.</hi> was it his <hi>ius</hi> to take from the people their fields and vineyards, and beſt oliue yards to giue to his ſervants? As is ſaid, <hi>ver. 14.</hi> How then ſinned <hi>Achab</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">1. Reg 21.1, 2, 3.</note> in coveting the vineyard of <hi>Naboth?</hi> And deſiring to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe it with mony? Yea, why offers he mony or deales by way of contract? It was his <hi>ius</hi> being a king, to take vineyards &amp; fields from ſubiects to giue to his ſerva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts: much more to keepe for his owne benefit and conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency. 3. Alienation of poſſeſſions from tribes and fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:17338:21"/> was flatly forbidden to the Iewiſh people, that Chriſts linage and deſcent might bee kept vnconfoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
            <p n="2">2 But what when it is yeelded hee had a <hi>tus</hi> to exact tithes of ſubiects? Muſt it needs be vnderſtood of tithes of Levits aſſigned them of God? and not rather of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tithes which he might craue in <hi>ſubſidium?</hi> as<note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 47.24.</note> fifts were once impoſed vpon Egyptians. Certainely <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chias,</hi> it ſeemes, thought tithes the Levits due, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore amongſt other precepts of reformation,<note place="margin">2. <hi>par.</hi> 31. 4. 5. 6</note> requires their paiment to Levi, as thinking tithes committed to him (if at all to him) but as Church goods of old were vnto Biſhops, <hi>non ut dominis,</hi> but <hi>ut oeconomis.</hi> And the people bring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to Levites in the name of holy things that were conſecrated vnto God.</p>
            <p>Apoſtles received not tithes in their daies. <hi>Ergo. Reſp.</hi> That is hard, that I ſay not, (impoſſible to proue) 2. not tithes, no nor ought els of ſome churches, but made their owne hands miniſter to their neceſſities, that they might not be ſcandalous to weake brethren, nor charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to afflicted churches; 3. yea ſuffered bonds, repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, cruell deaths, &amp;c. muſt therefore the Churches of all ages receiue like meaſure from her children? 4 The queſtion is <hi>de iure non de facto:</hi> &amp; that <hi>ius</hi> was remitted, becauſe burthenſome to thoſe times, as circumciſion was in the wildernes, <hi>Ioſhua. 5.5.6.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If tithes be thus due to Miniſters, why not alſo firſt fruits for theſe alſo were commanded to be paid to Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vits? <hi>Reſp.</hi> To theſe and all arguments following, this generall anſwere may ſerue; that wee claime not tithes by vertue of the precept given for Levites. Who ever
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:17338:21"/> heard vs thus reaſon? God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded tithes to be paide to Levites: <hi>Ergo</hi> tithes are due to the Miniſters of the Goſpell. But thus we claime them; as due to God by reſervation from the beginning, as following Chriſts prieſthood, as the only certainety mentioned in ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as conſecrated to God by conſent of Churches &amp; Edicts of princes, as agreeing with the vſe and practiſe of the Church in al times For the mandate of God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Levi, we make it not the ground of our title to tithes. So that of theſe reaſons we may ſay as he, they are <hi>Nihil ad Rhombum.</hi> Yet that nothing be wanting to anie mans ſatisfaction, I anſwer, 1. that firſt fruits were paid to <hi>Aaron,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Heb. 7 11</note> as to high prieſt, whoſe prieſthood is now paſſed to another; 2. vpon a reaſon particular to that people; 3. for ſacrifice, as appeares at large, <hi>De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 26. 2. ad 11.</hi> appeares there any ſuch thing of Tithes? Laſtly they were figures as ſhould ſeeme, of Chriſt,<note n="e" place="margin">1 Cor 15.20.</note> 
               <hi>The firſt fruits of them that ſleepe;</hi> of beginnings of ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, called by the Apoſtle<note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 8.23.</note> 
               <hi>the firſt fruits of the ſpirit.</hi> Can any of theſe be avouched of tithes? Who the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſees not manifeſt diſparity betweene the two?</p>
            <p>If this be a duty of people to pay tithes to Miniſters: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that alſo of Miniſters to<note n="g" place="margin">Num. 18.28.</note> 
               <hi>pay tithes to the high Prieſt. Reſp.</hi> The argument proceedes from a falſe <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> ſuppoſing vs to claime tithes by mandate Leviticall. Which we vtterly diſclaime, <hi>vt ſupra.</hi> 2. But yet farther I anſwere; It followes not if one, then the other due. 1. For<note n="h" place="margin">Pſ 50 12.13</note> 
               <hi>that our high Prieſt needs them not:</hi> but only hath ordained for them that<note n="i" place="margin">1. Cor 9.14.</note> preach the goſpel. 2. Sacrifices are now ceaſed, to which theſe <hi>Decimae ſecu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>daneae</hi> chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſerved<note n="k" place="margin">Num. 18.28 29.30.</note>; ſo that their reaſon is no more but this, If
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:17338:22"/> tithes for ſtipend, then tithes for ſacrifice: he is meerely <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that diſcernes not the inconſequence.</p>
            <p>If precept of tithing be moral, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that alſo of<note n="l" place="margin">Mal. 3 10.</note> brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging them to <hi>one common ſtorehouſe. Reſp.</hi> This argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t alſo proceedeth from like fained <hi>Hypotheſis.</hi> ſee <hi>ſupra.</hi> &amp; yet hath no good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequence: for muſt the ſubſtance of a duty needs be Levitical, becauſe ſome circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtances thereof concern only Iewiſh nation? The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt Sabbath alſo eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for ſubſtance be ceremoniall, becauſe ſome cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances &amp; ends belong only to Iews <hi>Deut. 5.15.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If precept of tithes be moral, then that alſo of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters not<note n="m" place="margin">Num. 18.24</note> 
               <hi>having portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amongſt their brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Reſp.</hi> The ſame fallacy that before; for we claime not by precept given to <hi>Levi.</hi> And yet the argument follows not. 1. for ſaith <hi>Polanus</hi> (though I avow not his anſwere) that or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance was figuratiue;<note place="margin">Polan in E<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>zech. <hi>44.</hi> v. <hi>28.</hi>
               </note> foreſhaddowing Chriſt that had not where to lay his head. But 2 it was never forbid<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den Levits to haue portion amongſt their brethren in that ſenſe that theſe men take portion. They<note n="n" place="margin">Numb. 35. Levit. 25.34.</note> 
               <hi>Had cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties with their ſuburbs</hi> which were their <hi>perpetuall poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> and paſſed from father to ſonne; ſubiect to ſame lawes of Redemption as others. Wherefore <hi>Ieremie</hi> a Prieſtes ſonne<note n="o" place="margin">Ier. 32.7.9.</note> buies the fielde of his vnckle as next of kin. See alſo <hi>1. King. 2.26.</hi> Thus therfore vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that ordinance of Levits having no portion amongſt their brethren. No portion, that is, no ſuch portion, ſeparate fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their brethren, as had other tribes, not ſimply none: the Reaſon thereof was <hi>Iacobs</hi> prophecy<note n="p" place="margin">Gen. 49.7.</note> touching <hi>their ſcattering amongſt their brethren.</hi> Diſpoſed of alſo by Gods providence for greater conveniency of the peoples inſtruction, as alſo by ſituation of their citties in<note n="q" place="margin">Ioſh. 21.</note> every tribe is me thinks probable. Laſtly a manifeſt
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:17338:22"/> diſparity there is between the two. For the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Le<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vits ſucceeded their pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, &amp; were for ever to be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by Levits portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Not ſo the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Miniſters, except they be<note n="r" place="margin">1. Tim. 3. Titus. 1.</note> 
               <hi>approved, &amp; fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d meet for the miniſtery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly they obiect the place, <hi>Numb. 18.24.</hi> vnanſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, as they thinke, and ſuch as if a man but turne to with a wet finger, he ſhall preſently ſee tithing a cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monious ordinance. Now for my part I haue viewed the place, and with my beſt attention conſidered what may thence be deduced to proue it ceremoniall. Yet finde not that it concludes either the ordinance in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, or yet that Leviticall conſtitution to haue beene ceremonious, for thus wee muſt frame the Argument. If tithes were aſſigned to <hi>Levi</hi> for his ſervice in the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle: then is the ordinance of tithing meerely cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monious; for that ſervice was ceremoniall. But tithes were aſſigned to <hi>Levi</hi> for his ſervice in the taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle. <hi>Ergo. Reſp.</hi> 1. To ſay nothing that that particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar aſſignement concludes not the ordinance at large, but the ordinance for <hi>Levi</hi> only: I anſwere 2. that by as good inference they may proue reverence, obedience, defence of Miniſters, ceremonious duties, inaſmuch as even theſe alſo belonged to Levites for their ſervice in the tabernacle. For why muſt Iſraelits giue Levites ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, obedience, ſingular loue, &amp;c: but for their worke ſake? And what was their worke? But their ſervice in the tabernacle. So that now our people owe vs no more honour, obedience, loue, &amp;c.<note n="ſ" place="margin">1 Theſ. 5 12 13. Heb. 13.17.</note> 
               <hi>for our worke ſake,</hi> as it is preſcribed. For theſe all belonged to Levites for their ſervice in the tabernacle, which was ceremonious. Briefly; they were given to Levites for their ſervice in
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:17338:23"/> the tabernacle, <hi>non quâ tabernaculi;</hi> but <hi>quâ ſervice.</hi> And therefore before tabernacle erected, they were paide to Prieſts, <hi>Gen. 14.</hi> 3. Was the whole ſervice of the taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle ceremonious? Nay were not ſome maine parts of it, apparently morall? What thinke we of teaching the people?<note n="t" place="margin">2. Chr. 17.9. Act 15.21. Nehe. 8.3.6.7 8.</note> of <hi>Reading the ſcriptures, and giving ſenſe? of praiſing God?</hi> Were not theſe parts of tabernacle ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice? And had not the Levites maintenaunce for theſe, as well as for ſlaying ſacrifices? Surely if this be the beſt and cleareſt reaſons againſt tithing, I muſt needes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, they are ſo farre from making me doubt of my concluſion, that they rather ſtabliſh my iudgment ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. And theſe are all the arguments I haue yet heard vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by men of any iudgement, againſt the neceſſitie of paying tithes.</p>
            <p>One other only which ſeculars vſe, I will annexe; &amp; that is drawne from a perilous inconvenience enſuing vpon this doctrine. What is it? Forſooth if tithes belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to Miniſters &amp; are payable to them only, according to the word of God: it wil come to paſſe, that a Miniſters portion ſhall exceed the allowance of two or three of his wealthieſt pariſhioners. But that, I tell you, is a ſhrewd inconvenience. <hi>Reſp.</hi> A miſchiefe which I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Lord in his endleſſe wiſdome never bethought himſelfe to prevent amongſt the Iſraelits. The Levites, though according to the generall diviſion of Iſraell by tribes, they were but a twelfth or thirteenth part: yet according to exact number of perſons reckoned by polles, were ſcarce the ſixtith part of the people. The number of the people without the Levites, amounted to<note n="u" place="margin">Num. 1.46.</note> ſixe hundred and three thouſands, fiue hundred &amp;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17338:23"/> fifty; to which if we adde their old men, and al from vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der twenty yeares amongſt them which came not into the firſt number,<note n="x" place="margin">Numb. 1.3.</note> allowing but double ſo many for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they ariſe to about a thouſand thouſands and three hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſands. Now the Levites numbred from the infant to the old man, were found but two and twenty thouſands only,<note n="y" place="margin">Num. 3 39.</note> and that is not aboue the ſixtith part of the people. Yet ſee, the Lord allots them the tenth of all the increaſe of the land: beſides ſhare in oblations,<note n="z" place="margin">Num. 35 4.7</note> things conſecrate by vow, and 48. citties with ſuburbs of ſo large circuit, that according to <hi>Hieromes</hi> meaſure of the land, exceeded the portion of any other tribe in Iſraell. Its marvell none woulde vndertake to be the Lords Counſellour, and to tel him ſuch large allowance might make Levites prowde and lazy. But this large portion to the Lord ſeemed no inconvenience: howe ſeemes it ſo to vs, in Miniſters of the Goſpell?</p>
            <p>Againe, how fals it, that to other orders &amp; rankes of men, as lawyers, gentles, &amp;c. their portions excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding by more then fourths the portions of others, are not maligned; the Miniſters of all other ſhould bee ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to envie?</p>
            <p>Laſtly, how is it, that men in their own, though far larger portion, know no meaſure, but adde continually thouſands to hundreds; and (as <hi>Agars</hi> horſleach) crie, giue, giue; and as the graue, knowe no meaſure of deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring: yet of a miniſters ſtipend, of fiftie, or an hundred pounds, cry <hi>Sufficit;</hi> Its enough, and too much? What, I wonder, is that great ſervice theſe men performe, ſo over acceptable to God, or profitable vnto men, aboue the worke of a miniſter? that they ſhould thinke them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:17338:24"/> worthy of all, whatſoever by a <hi>vijs &amp; modis</hi> they can ſcrape togither; and yet to miniſters, for their work ſake, hardly beteeme double honour in proportion to the meane wealthy amongſt their people. <hi>Tempora, Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pora,</hi> how are yee turned? But I conclude. Sith Tithes be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>long to Chriſts prieſthood, ſith no other certainety al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotted to Miniſters in ſcriptures, ſith detainement is ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilege, ſith tithing no ceremony nor particularly Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall, ſith confirmed by conſent and practiſe of the Church in all times, laſtly (which is not the leaſt) ſith reaſons againſt it are of ſo no force, as wee haue ſeene: therefore tithes are the portion due to Miniſters for their ſervice in the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Concluſion.</note>What now remaines? but to admoniſh ſuch as feare God, to deliver their ſoules from the guilt of ſo fowle a ſinne as is this of ſacrilege. Why hang yee vp theeues that ſteale from men, oft times but as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith<note n="a" place="margin">Prov. 6.30.</note> 
               <hi>to ſatisfie their owne ſoules;</hi> and liue your ſelues in ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Mal. 3.8.</note> 
               <hi>rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery of God</hi> himſelfe? Far be it from mee to multiply ſins or to caſt vnneceſſary ſcruples into the conſciences of Gods people. But faine J would knowe for my lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, of ſuch as are ſo loth in this point to wound con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences (alas, how ſenſeleſſe, and fleſhed in ſacrilege!) where God hath ever legitimated ſacrilege; or made it lawfull vnder the new Teſtament, to alienate from him things conſecrated to his worſhip: when turned the truth of that ſentence into a lie;<note n="c" place="margin">Prov. 20.25 Rom. 2. Act. 5.1.3.</note> 
               <hi>It is a ſinne to devoure holy things, and after the vow to enquire.</hi> Nay the Lord it ſeemes, hath written it in the hearts of Naturaliſts with the point of a Diamond: howſoever ſome mens ſimple or wilful ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, or impious profanenes, or inſatiable
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:17338:24"/> covetouſnes ſeemes <hi>to detain this point of truth,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 1.58.</note> as many other, <hi>in vnrighteouſnes.</hi> Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Nabuchadnezzar</hi> had ſur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>priſed the temple, &amp; ſeized the ſacred veſſels appointed to Gods worſhip: in the middeſt of ſacriledge, he feares to be ſacrilegious; and therfore<note n="e" place="margin">Dan. 1.2.</note> 
               <hi>brings them to the houſe of his Gods,</hi> ſuppoſed by him to bee the only true Gods. Infinite I might be in propounding the ſentences, and cenſures, that heathen paſſed vpon this point of impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. And is there any man can doubt whither detaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of tithes be ſacriledge, or not? Shape to they ſelfe a deſcription of ſacriledge with any ſound limits deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining its nature, and ſee whither vnder it fals not the detainement of tithes. <hi>I beſeech you therefore ſuffer the words of exhortation: Giue Caeſar, Caeſars; and God, that which is Gods.</hi> Neede I, I thinke, to preſſe it by reaſons? Not ſure if the belly had eares. But ſweete ſinnes, are the dangerous ſinnes, becauſe for the moſt part incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigible; begetting in moſt, either a loathneſſe to bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, or obfirmation againſt all perſwaſions. Yet let vs attempt; who knows whither the Lord may be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed<note n="f" place="margin">Act 16 14.</note> 
               <hi>to open the heart,</hi> if but of one <hi>Lydia, to attend to the things which are ſpoken?</hi> Conſider therefore, I beſeech you, even in the bowels of Chriſt Ieſus; firſt the hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſneſſe of this ſinne of ſacriledge. They erre in<note n="g" place="margin">Zanch. de vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiis exter. Cult. oppoſit. Theſi <hi>3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Za<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies</hi> iudgement, that make ſacriledge only a branch of theft, and breach of the eighth precept; yea rather it is a <hi>ſpecies</hi> of irreligion. Heare his reaſons. For whence proceedes it; but from contempt of holy things, &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt vnreverence towards God himſelfe? wherefore ſteales any man things ſeparate to preſerue the miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, but becauſe he contemnes the whole Miniſtery, yea
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:17338:25"/> God himſelfe to whoſe worſhippe they are conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted?</p>
            <p>And wherevnto tendes ſuch fraudulent, or violent praying vpon holy things: but to the vtter overthrow of all religion? Sathan knowes well, Gods outwarde worſhip cannot be continued without the Miniſterie, nor the Miniſtery without Miniſters, nor Miniſters without Church goods: and therefore provokes hee <hi>Tyrants and profane men,</hi> to invade the Churches poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions, that by that meanes he may hinder, if not whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly overthrowe, the ſtate of religion. To this purpoſe <hi>Zanchius.</hi> Shall I adde one other reaſon? The rather becauſe I ſee men thinke of this theft, even thoſe that thinke worſt, but as of thefts from men; they rob not God, but Miniſters (if any) while they detaine tithes, or other things hallowed. Now let them conſider, that the dominion, and propertie of all things hallowed, is Gods, and ſuch conſecration giues him ſeizure of them in ſee; the vſe only is the Miniſters.<note n="h" place="margin">Polan. in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zech. <hi>48.14.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Quae ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficata ſunt Domino, non ſunt eorum, quibus data ſunt, ſed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius, cuius nomine poſſidentur.</hi> Things hallowed to God, are not ſo much theirs, to whom they are given, as Gods in whoſe title they are poſſeſſed. Therefore (ſaith the Lord to the Iſraelites detaining tithes from the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vits) <hi>Yee</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Mal. 3.</note> 
               <hi>haue robbed not Levi, whoſe they are in vſe, but</hi> ME, <hi>in whom is the property and dominion.</hi> Need any more reaſons, then the enormity of the ſinne? Heare then 2 the deteſtation wherein in al times amongſt all men, chriſtians, or heathen, this ſin was holden. To omit the bitter invectiues every where obvious, conſider the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments appointed for the ſacrilegious.<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cent.</hi> 9. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>Charles</hi> the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:17338:25"/> great in his time made this decree; that whoſoever ſhould invade, or waſte, or by any cunning meanes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to alienate the goods of the church, he ſhould le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally be puniſhed by the Iudges, as an homicide, or ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegious theefe, excommunicated by the Biſhops, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of burial; yea, as if his almes were infectious, or accurſed, none muſt receiue it. Amongſt the heathen no tortures were thought ſufficient for this ſin,<note n="l" place="margin">Lactant. de orig. Error. c. <hi>3</hi>
               </note> ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gings, burnings, rackings, hangings, any thing whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever their furie could deviſe to inflict.<note n="m" place="margin">Plutarch. de his qui ſerò a numine puniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note> At Delphos they vſed to caſt them headlong from a rocke, which they called <hi>Hyampeia.</hi> The <hi>Aethiopians</hi> had an herb they called <hi>Ophiuſa,</hi> as of vnpleaſing aſpect, ſo of farre more dangerous effect taken into the body. It ſo affrighted with phantaſmes of dreadfull ſerpents, that ſuch as dra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k it made away themſelues.<note n="n" place="margin">Plin. hiſt. nat. lib. <hi>26.</hi> cap. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Obid</hi> (ſaith <hi>Pliny) cogebantur ſacrilegi illam bibere;</hi> for that cauſe were church robbers forced to drinke it.</p>
            <p>Amongſt our ſelues, breaking vp of churches, &amp; ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the leaſt trifle, aggravates the theft, &amp; makes the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender culpable of death. If the Philoſopher were now aliue, would he not laugh at the ſpectacle? To ſee the great theeues lead the ſmaller to the gallows? How is it a ſin more hainous, to violate a temple, then to alienate Church maintenance from the worſhip of God? 3. If none of theſe moue, oh yet let the blood of ſo manie ſoules periſhing by this, if not as a cauſe, yet as a greate occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, waken vs. Many motions I haue heard of, made for a learned miniſtery, that every congregation might haue<note n="o" place="margin">Ier. 3.15.</note> 
               <hi>a past or to feed them with knowledge and vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</hi> For my part I ſay as<note n="p" place="margin">Gal. 5.12.</note> 
               <hi>Paule</hi> in another caſe; <hi>vtina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:17338:26"/> excindantur;</hi> I would they were cut off that hinder it. But amongſt all, how is it that the point of mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance comes not to be conſulted? It were to be wiſhed that the Apoſtolique zeale burnt now in Miniſters, that rather then ſoules ſhould ſtarue, they would freely giue what they haue freely receaved. But hee was<note n="q" place="margin">Perkins in Iob. <hi>33. 23.</hi>
               </note> an holie man that ſaid, men are men, and muſt be allured by ſuch arguments as may prevaile even with fleſh and blood. It was Gods great wiſdome in the creation, firſt to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide food, before he made the <hi>Animal creatures.</hi> And it's aſhame to the Church in the daies of peace, to ſee men of beſt gifts therefore divert their ſtudies to other arts, becauſe the miniſtery affords not maintenance; for our Church moſt, where Gods allowance is ſo liberall, were it not that ſacrilege did intercept it.</p>
            <p n="4">4 May J not adde the miſchiefe temporall it hath brought vpon the land? Complaints are frequent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt our people againſt incloſures the decayers (they ſay) of husbandry, by which, ſaith <hi>Salomon,</hi> even kings are maintained. I dare ſay, that <hi>peculatus,</hi> if J may ſo tearme it, hath not beene more hurtfull this way, then hath this ſacrilege. Cornefields were wont to laugh in our Gentlemens now paſtures; but tithes ſeeme more compendious to the ground of houſekeeping then the toileſome tediouſneſſe of tilling the earth. And <hi>ſcarfe a great man</hi> now adaies, though but niggardly hoſpitall, that can keep open dores without a Parſonage. It were wel me thinkes amongſt ſo many delicates, they would once in their liues eate one morcel of their own bread. Laſtly, if theſe perſwade not, yet let that terrour of the Lord prevaile with vs;<note n="r" place="margin">Prov. 20.25.</note> 
               <hi>Its a curſe</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon) to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voure
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:17338:26"/> holy things, a curſed practiſe,</hi> that brings downe Gods vengeance vpon the ſacrilegious.</p>
            <p>Examples we haue ſeene many, and read of more: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven kings themſelues haue not gone vnpuniſhed. The<note n="ſ" place="margin">Zech. 5.4.</note> 
               <hi>flying booke</hi> of Gods vengance, <hi>Enter</hi> (ſaith <hi>Zecherie) into the houſe of the theefe, and conſumes it with the timber, and the ſtones thereof; leaues ſcarſe a monument where hee hath beene.</hi> Is God thus ſharpe againſt petite thefts, and will he leaue ſacrilege vnavenged? Search records di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, humane: where findeſt thou a rob-God without his vengance? obſerue theſe ſacrilegious amongſt our ſelues: its much if they proſper to the fourth generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; much, (though God be much in ſparing) if hee either leaue not them childleſſe, or their children graceleſſe, by one meanes or other makes them not vomit thoſe morſels of holy things, that they haue devoured. Tithes with lay men, are as the<note n="t" place="margin">1. Sam. 5 6.9.11.</note> Arke with the Philiſtims, pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing the vniuſt poſſeſſors, til they returne to the right owners.</p>
            <p>Enough I hope of this firſt ſinne. And too much per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>haps ſome wil ſay, too ful of tartnes. Let them remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the <hi>Callum</hi> is thicke, and needs a hot <hi>Cauterie.</hi> Yea but it may wound the conſcience; <hi>Vtinam.</hi> The remedy is at hand. <hi>Reſtituatur ablatum, vt dimittatur peccatum.</hi> Howſoever, for my ſoule, I dare not<note n="u" place="margin">Iſai. 5.20.</note> 
               <hi>ſpeake good of evill,</hi> Read <hi>Ezech. 13.22.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 As to our people, wittie, alas, to their own harme, in ſhifting to detaine that little of the Lords portion ſtill left him, I ſay as<note n="*" place="margin">2 Par. 31.4.</note> 
               <hi>Hezechias</hi> (J would, I could hope with like ſucceſſe) Giue the portion to Prieſts, and Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vits, to Miniſters of the Goſpell, that they may bee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:17338:27"/> in the law of the Lord. Needes any more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons then the encouragement of your Miniſters. Heare <hi>Malachy;</hi> Detainment is robbery in the higheſt degree; ſacrilege;<note n="x" place="margin">Mal. 3 10.</note> 
               <hi>yee haue robbed mee,</hi> ſaith the Lord to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders. 2. Robberie deteſted by Jdolaters; <hi>will a man, will an Idolater ſpoile his Gods?</hi> For ſhame let not Chriſtians ſpoile their God. 3<note n="y" place="margin">Levit. 27 30</note> 
               <hi>Tithes are Gods</hi> by reſervation fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning, Miniſters are but his receavers. 4. Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>ſets open the wondowes of heaven, and brings downe a bleſsing in abundance; 5. Detainement, a curſe, yea vpon whole kingdomes.</hi> That ſaying of <hi>Salomon,</hi> let never bee forgotten;<note n="z" place="margin">Prov. 3.9.10</note> 
               <hi>Honour God with thy ſubſtance and with the chiefe of all thine increaſe: ſo ſhall thy barnes be filled with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance;</hi> is a bleſſing annexed to this dutie. Will any ſay its ſpoken only for that ſtate of the Church in Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el? Let him pervſe the whole booke, and inſtance but in one precept there given of Leviticall performances, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he will too abſurdly <hi>inſtare in propoſito.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>More perſwaſions I wil not adde: how feare I, that J ſhall not perſwade, no not though J doe perſwade? Shal J preſume to ſpeake of the figleaues, men haue ſowne to themſelues to hide their ſhame? Some thus: To ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt able Miniſters they thinke them due; but diſhoneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie &amp;c. makes vncapable. <hi>Reſp.</hi> With what conſcience then detaine yee from ſuch whoſe honeſty and abilitie your ſelues will teſtifie? 2 The Levites in <hi>Malachie</hi> his daies<note n="a" place="margin">Mal. 2.7, 8, 9</note> 
               <hi>had broken the covenant, were become ignorant, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall, contemptible:</hi> yet even in thoſe times called the Lord for tithes. 3. What law of God, or man, permits to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate men detainment of dues even from the diſhoneſt.<note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 22.</note> 
               <hi>To wicked Magiſtrats tribute muſt be paid.</hi> 4. Tithes are
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:17338:27"/> due to Miniſters, not <hi>quâ probi;</hi> but <hi>quâ miniſtri:</hi> not for their honeſty; but for their Miniſterie.</p>
            <p>As to thoſe other obiections, of cuſtomes,<note place="margin">Vae tibi flumen moris humanit quamdiu non ſiccaberis? Aug. confeſſ.</note> preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, exemptions &amp;c. I ſay no more, but what the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle in this caſe;<note n="c" place="margin">Gal. 6.7.</note> 
               <hi>God is not mocked.</hi> A pretty mocke-God anſwere it will bee, at that great day when thou ſhalt ſtand before the great <hi>Proprietarie</hi> to bee exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, how faithfully thou haſt given Tithes according to his aſſignement; to tell him: for matter of tithing, thou hadſt a cuſtome to the contrary. Dally not with conſcience, deceaue not thy ſelfe, God ſure wil not thus be deluded.</p>
            <p>Thus far of this queſtion at your requeſt; to whome vndeſerved kindneſſe hath engaged mee ſo farre, as my weake abilities can extend themſelus. Of this tract thus thinke; The Author thinketh himſelfe a man, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſubiect to errour. Yet would faine ſo carry himſelf, as to deſerue of Gods Church the eſteeme of an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt man, and therefore no lover of errors; much leſſe a Patrone of them againſt his knowledge and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:17338:28"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17338:28"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
